<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Italie: or, A prodigious, and most lamentable accident, latelie befallen concerning the swallowing vp of the whole citie of Pleurs: belonging vnto the Signiorie of Venice. Which happened in the beginning of September last past: by a strange and hideous shaking, and opening of the earth. Together with the losse of moe than two thousande people: and a generall burning vp of the trees and forrests within the territories of the said citie. Faythfullie translated out of the French copie, printed at Paris, 1618.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837151</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 991:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Italie: or, A prodigious, and most lamentable accident, latelie befallen concerning the swallowing vp of the whole citie of Pleurs: belonging vnto the Signiorie of Venice. Which happened in the beginning of September last past: by a strange and hideous shaking, and opening of the earth. Together with the losse of moe than two thousande people: and a generall burning vp of the trees and forrests within the territories of the said citie. Faythfullie translated out of the French copie, printed at Paris, 1618.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Andro Hart,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Newes from Italy.</note>
                  <note>Pleurs = Piuro.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Earthquakes --  Piuro (Italy) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:1461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Tudor rose</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>a blazon with the monogram of 'A' (Andro) superimposed on ♡ (Hart)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Scottish thistle</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>NEWES FROM ITALIE: <hi>OR,</hi> A prodigious, and moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Accident, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>befallen:</hi> Concerning the ſwallowing vp of the whole Citie <hi>of</hi> PLEVRS: <hi>Belonging to the Signiorie of</hi> VENICE.</p>
            <p>Which happened in the beginning of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>laſt paſt: by a ſtrange and hideous ſhaking,</hi> and opening of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Together with the loſſe of moe than two thouſande <hi>People: and a generall burning vp of the Trees and</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts within the Territories of the ſaid Citie.</p>
            <p>Faythfullie tranſlated out of the French Copie,</p>
            <p>Printed at PARIS, 1618.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Scottish thistle</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by <hi>Andro Hart. Anno Domini</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1461:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:1461:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <head>A Prodigious, and moſt lamentable accident, <hi>Lately befallen the Citie of</hi> PLEVRS, Belonging to the Signiorie of VENICE: <hi>Which happened in the beginning of</hi> September laſt paſt, 1618.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch is the prauitie of our nature, that wee alwayes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feele the ſmart of Gods Diuine vengeance falling vpon vs, than weigh the counſels and purpoſe of his heart, which hee aymeth at in the midſt of his wrath, puniſhing and correcting vs for our juſt deſerts, by which wee haue couſtrained him to turne his mercy into juſtice, and fauour and benefits, into rods and ſcourges.</p>
            <p>The effects whereof falling out daily before our
<pb facs="tcp:1461:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->eyes, in this behalfe, tende to none other ende, but to rowze vs out of that lethargie of ſin into which wee bee fallen, and to let out the ſwelling of our pride: that at the length wee may carefullie aduiſe our ſelues, before our finall deſolation fall vpon our heads. But (alas) wee are ſo hood-winked, and ſenſeleſſe, in the middeſt of this our miſerie, that for want of a diſcerning eye, wee are readie to attribute all miſſe-happe to ſecondarie cauſes, and to extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie effectes: rather than wiſelie to bethinke vs, in judging, that the roote from whence all our euils ſpring, is from our ſelues.</p>
            <p>From none other cauſe proceedeth all the caſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which happen euerie day in our ſight: but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie of late yeares, as well by the laſt effectes of Fire, Aire, and Water, as by other vnawonted acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, proceeding from the elementes, which God vſeth as his roddes to afflict man withall.</p>
            <p>Wee know, that within a yeare, or there abouts, what hath hapned both in <hi>France,</hi> and elſewhere, to the great aſtoniſhment of mortall men, who are but duſt and aſhes, and whereat indeed the greateſt wits haue ſtood amazed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spaine</hi> was at her wittes ende, in admiring that Deluge which befell in the Earledome of <hi>Barcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonne,</hi> with much ruine and loſſe in this verie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and time of the yeare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1461:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
               <hi>France</hi> it ſelfe hath had no cauſe to mocke at her Neighboures harmes, but to bee vvhollie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp vvith feare, hauing ſeene, the Lenton laſt paſt, 1618. the vvonderfull burning and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the Pallace of her head Citie; the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Innocent, the terrour of the guiltie, where the Oracles of Trueth were euerie daye to bee hearde, by vncorrupt ARISTIDES, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible in the cauſe of Equitie, and a juſt conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Right and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But all this is but a little, in reſpect of that, which as wee heare, hapned vpon the Countreyes belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Signiorie of VENICE, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this preſent moneth of September, to the ruine and vtter loſſe of the Towne, or Citie, of PLEVRS: namelie, that about that time, the fourth, or the fifth, of this preſent moneth, happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon the Territories of the ſaide Cittie ſuch a fearfull and prodigious ſtorme, mingled with thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and lightnings, with winde and tempeſt, that it ſeemed Heauen and Earth woulde haue gone to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and that the laſt times, fore-tolde by <hi>Daniel,</hi> were nowe inflicted there: and that which is worthy of greateſt wonder and aſtoniſhment, was an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vehement winde, encloſed and ſhutte vppe within the bowels &amp; hollowneſſe of the earth, with certaine fires burning vnder the grounde, vvhich vvith their violent encountering each of other,
<pb facs="tcp:1461:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->with blaſts, &amp; counter-blaſts, made ſuch an hideous noyſe within thoſe holes and narrow places, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Countrey was filled, that it cauſed a verie ſtrange ſhaking, or trembling, of the Earth: yea, ſo fearfull, that the effects enſuing thereof are incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible: Thence came the totall and deplorable loſſe of the ſaid Citie of PLEVRS, ſomewhat greater, and better peopled, than is S. <hi>Denis</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> For the Earth opening it ſelfe, by the vehemencie of theſe fires vnder the ground, and the bluſteringes of theſe winds incloſed within her bowels, and in ſeeking vent, that in this opening and trembling of the earth, the ſaid City was wholly ſunken and ſwallowed vp, with all and euery one of the houſes and buildings, with the loſſe of moe than two thouſande ſoules, crauing for mercy in ſo great, ſo ſudden, and vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected a calamity. And within the ſaid Territorie, many Trees, Woods, &amp; Forreſts, were ſome of them ouerthrowne by the windes, and otherſome were conſumed and burnt, aſwell by the fire of heauen, as by the flames iſſuing foorth, and vomited from out of the bowels of the earth: VVhich ſtrucke ſuch an aſtoniſhment into the neighbour Countreyes, that all fell to prayers, made publicke and ſolemne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions: taking it for a certain forewarning of Gods mercy turned into fury, and for a ſure vndoubted token, that his anger is kindled againſt the ſonnes of men: ſeeking hereby to appeaſe him in the midſt of his juſt concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued diſpleaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1461:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <head>The former Relation, More particularly ſet foorth, in an <hi>Aviſo, of the Lordes of the</hi> States of HELVETIA and the GRISONS.</head>
            <head type="sub">Faythfully tranſlated, according to the Copie Printed at <hi>MILLAINE, 1618.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE effects of Nature are of ſo deepe comprehenſion, as the moſt ſubtill Philoſophers haue loſt themſelues in the admiration thereof. The flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and ebbe of an <hi>Eury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> made him loſe all his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who laboured to ſettle the principles and groundes therof: And he who ſo ſearched into the courſe and originall of it, returned from thence aſtoniſhed with wonder, and beſotted with ignorance. In briefe, her ſecrets are ſo darke and hidden, as mortall eyes can
<pb facs="tcp:1461:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->make no diſcouerie thereof: God, the Author of Nature, reſeruing, as a particular to himſelfe, the knowledge of thoſe myſteries, with a barre to all others to enter into them. And if man can challenge to himſelfe any little taſte thereof, he hath it by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe from that great diſtributer of knowledge, and with the price of paines and trauels innumerable.</p>
            <q>Dii laboribus omnia vendunt.</q>
            <p>The accident which happened in freſh memorie, about a moneth ſince, in a certaine Towne called <hi>Pleurs,</hi> ſubject to the State of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> a people confining with the Territorie of <hi>Millaine,</hi> and with <hi>Switzer-land,</hi> cannot but beget in vs both aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and admiration together: aſtoniſhment, for the ſtrangeneſſe: admiration, in that we are not able to comprehend the cauſe and ground thereof. This is not the fable of remouing mountaines, &amp; heaping one vpon the top of another by <hi>Ouids</hi> gyants, to ſcale Heauen withal: but a true fact, which as it made the Earth to tremble, ſo may it doe the heartes of the moſt couragious men, and make them ſhake, by ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king things, to all mens thought, immooueable: ſo as nowe wee can grounde no firme aſſurance vpon Rockes, and Chaunge reigneth by courſe ouer all thinges. This Towne of <hi>Pleurs,</hi> aboue named, ſeated vpon the land, and amongſt the people of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> is ſubject for the Temporalities, vnto the Lordes of that State: and for the Spiritualities, in as much as it is whollie Popiſh, (excepting onelie
<pb facs="tcp:1461:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->three or foure houſes,) it is vnder the juriſdiction of the Biſhop of <hi>Como.</hi> It is rich, well peopled, famous for Trade, the Kirkes (well recommended for their building, rich Ornamentes, and Treaſure,) ſeeme ſufficientlie to witneſſe the pietie of that people. One of them was conſecrate vnder the name of Sainct <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Silan:</hi> and the other, more renowned than that, by the name of Sainct <hi>Caſsian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The particulars as well of this Countrey, as of this Towne, which are not indeede of our diſcourſe, cannot but bee tedious to the Reader, who atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with impatience the newes of a caſe ſo ſtrange as this is. This Towne is in a Valley, vnder the mountaine <hi>Chrouena,</hi> in neare neighbourhood, and not aboue the diſtance of two leagues from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Millaine:</hi> and of like neareneſſe to the Porte of <hi>Tuentes;</hi> ſtanding vpon the banke of the Lake of <hi>Como,</hi> where paſſeth the Riuer of <hi>Mora:</hi> which Riuer, although it carrie a ſtrong and violent current, yet can it not, in anie reaſon, be preſumed to haue beene the cauſe of this ruine vvhereof vvee are to ſpeake. Nature had fortified this Towne, and immured it, as it were, betwixt two mountains: the one whereof was ſingularlie fertile in Winter, and other Fruites of the Earth making her appeare with another cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, than of an hideous Rock: which could promiſe no pleaſure nor delight, but of ſuch an Hill as ſupplyed the Inhabitantes with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite commodities, vnder-ground Caues, &amp; Gardens,
<pb facs="tcp:1461:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->Store-houſes; and other commodious places, which they found within the boſome of this mountaine, with all ſorts of pleaſures, delightes, and delicates. This other Hill, which is aboue <hi>Silano,</hi> and beyond the Riuer, is ſomewhat more diſtant from the Town, which, it ſeemeth, Nature had purpoſely remooued from the ſame, leſt it might (perhaps) too much ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and obſcure it, that the great multitude of trees wherewith this Hill was repleniſhed, being of it ſelfe higher and ſteeper than the former, and yet bearing (notwithſtanding the ſteepeneſſe) both hay and wood, for the ſupply of this Towne. Cloſe to this mountaine there ſtood another, much higher than the ſame, and wholly barrend and deſarted: a fatall Hill, and deſtined to the ruine of this miſerable Towne, and all her inhabitants.</p>
            <p>The fourth day of this inſtant month of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, this great and ſteepe Hill was ſhaken, either by ſome windes vnder the ground, or by ſome ſecret tempeſt which Nature raiſed from within her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels: in ſuch fort, as about ſix a clock in the euening, that which ſeemed to be vnmoueable, was ſeene in a ſhort ſpace to be pulled vp by the roots, and borne away by the fury of the windes. A ſtrange caſe, there neuer hauing beene ſeene ſo great and fearfull an Earth-quake. This mountaine then being ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with his fury, fell with ſuch violence vpon that vnhappy Towne, as it buried both it, and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants together. It was about Supper-time, at
<pb facs="tcp:1461:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->what time the moſt parte of the Townesmen were ſet at Table, when they found themſelues ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with theſe ſo mightie ruines, vnder which, at an inſtant they gaue vppe the ghoſt. Scarcelie was any man exempted, for of three thouſand &amp; ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth perſons, which at that time were reckoned to bee in the Towne, there eſcaped onelie foure, of whome wee will ſpeake more particularlie heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The loſſe of goods was exceeding great, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the eſteemate thereof paſſeth three Millions of Golde. The rage and tempeſtuous force of the windes was ſo outragious, as they that were in the fieldes felt themſelues thereby transported into pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whollie vnknowne. The Lord <hi>Laurence Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolera</hi> reporteth, that being in a Garden of his, with his Niece, hee was borne by the violence of that tempeſt aboue and beyonde the Riuer: and hee was found on a little Hill, called <hi>Ronco,</hi> hauing a Napkin at his Shoulder, and his Legges broken off. In the ſame place were likewiſe founde the little Belles of Sainct <hi>Maries</hi> Kirke, borne by the like violence out of the Steeple to that place, being halfe a league from the ſaide Kirke. To conclude, this boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing was ſo terrible, and the bruit ſpread ſo farre, that all the neighbouring Countreyes preſently took the cry, and ſtood affrighted with the horror thereof.</p>
            <p>The people comming a little to themſelues, ran to beholde this ſpectacle, vvhere in ſtead of finding a Towne, in the Valleye before mentioned, they
<pb facs="tcp:1461:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->found an high and fearfull mountaine, hauing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its entralls ſwallowed the whole company of its poore inhabitants: no man eſcaping, ſaue only four, as were ſaide, whom wee will name in particular, to giue more aſſurance to the trueth of the fact.</p>
            <p>A Mother there deſirous to ſaue her Childe, loſt her legges, yet could not recouer him whome ſhee held deareſt in the worlde. A young man, called <hi>Francis Torno,</hi> who was gone down into one of the Vaults vnder ground (which before we mentioned, and deſcribed in the firſt Mountaine) to draw wine. Another young fellow, who a little before was gone to a Vineyarde, on the ſame mountaine, to gather Peaches. And the fourth was the Lord <hi>Scandolera,</hi> of whom we before recounted that miraculous ſtory.</p>
            <p>The Riuer <hi>Mora,</hi> which watered all this Valley, hath thereby loſt its naturall and ordinary current: and hath beene enforced to recouer its courſe more than a league from the place. This is the ſumme of what happened in the places afore ſaid, being in trueth a wonder vnmatchable in any Age.</p>
            <p>The Deeps below, and Fire aboue, hold ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary power of Nature: but to ſee mountains remoue, and change their places, wee muſt in trueth auouch, that this thing is ſo high, and the cauſes ſo hidden, as humane wit cannot pierce into the depth of theſe profound myſteries. To make Nature ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1461:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->potent, as to giue occaſion for the vvorld to thinke, that this accident proceeded from the force of the winds, which perhaps were ſhut vp within the womb of the Earth, and there had intermixed with ſome encloſed fire, which hauing vndermined this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, did in ſuch ſort ouerturne it, were to attribute vnto Nature too much force and ſtrength. To call to remembrance another <hi>Sodome,</hi> wherof this is the image, the colours only excepted, I meane the forme of their deſtruction: to aſcribe this calamitie to the judgement of God, were to partake with the ſecrets of the Higheſt, and as companions to his Throne, to giue ſentence againſt his people. Therefore, ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our judgements, let vs humble our ſelues before God, leſt the like thing happen vnto vs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
